A Guide to the Mary Lou Drosten Architectural Collection,
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Mary Lou Drosten Architectural Collection,
1911-1990
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2016-008
9.0 cu. ft.
Biographical Note
Mary Lou Drosten was born on July 5, 1910 in St. Louis, Missouri. Drosten attended Washington University in St. Louis from 1928-1933. There, she received a B.A. in Architecture. After graduation, Drosten became a caseworker. In 1937, Drosten married Fred Drosten. Mary Lou Drosten and Fred Drosten had four children. Throughout her life, Drosten lived in St. Louis, MO; Oak Ridge, TN; Nicaro, Cuba; Chattanooga, TN; Huntsville, AL; and retired in St. Louis, MO. In Chattanooga, TN, Mary Lou owned Drosten Design and worked on many projects. Some projects of note include a building design for a dental surgeon (1934), 7-room residence for the Drosten family in Chevy Chase (1937), and proposal for a new hospital for polio in Des Moines (1942). Despite Drosten suffering from polio, she continued to work in the architectural field. Drosten died on November 16, 1991.
Scope and Content
The Mary Lou Drosten Architectural Collection documents Mary Lou Drosten’s personal and professional life as an architect. The collection contains Mary Lou Drosten’s personal papers, including biographic information such as newspaper articles documenting Mary Lou Drosten's contraction of polio and her remarkable recovery. Mary Lou Drosten collected newspaper articles, advertisements, and other material on social inequality. Drosten's primary interest was women's rights, but she also collected materials on racial discrimination. Mary Lou Droston's professional papers include associations and committees such as the Association of Women in Architecture, Huntsville League of Women Voters, and Congress on American Women Leaders. In addition, Drosten maintained project records, including research materials, financial records, contracts, photographs, and detailed drawings.
Arrangement
Arrangement of these materials follows the original order established by the creator and the Standard Series for Architecture and Landscape Design Records (Shepherd and Lowell). Project records are ranged alphabetically by client name. The intellectual structure reflects the following series and subseries:
I. Personal Papers
A. Biographical Information
B. Student Work
C. Civic Society
II. Professional papers
A. Associations and Committees
B. Conferences
C. Writings
D. Research Notes
E. Reference Files
III. Office Records
IV. Project Records
Separated Materials
The following books were separated from the collection to be cataloged for the Rare Book Collection: Neutra, R. Survival Through Design, 1969. Wright, F.L. An American Architecture. Wright, F.L. The Natural House. The 1940 Book of Small Houses. House & Gardens New Complete Guide to Interior Decoration. Doctor's Offices.<
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); History of Women in Architecture; Women-owned architectural firms; Women architects -- Tennessee; Women architects -- Missouri
- Series I: Personal Papers
  - Biographical Information
    - Biography - Mary Lou Drosten (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Biographies/"Who's Who?" (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Employment/Application Letters (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Drosten Residence in Huntsville (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Architectural Projects List (by Family) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Student Work
    - Beginning 1930, Design etc. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Math and Architecture (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Materials (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Architecture History (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ornament (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Elements of Architecture (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Geology (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Playground Course (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - History of Art (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Architecture Course Notes (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Washington University, Architecture 42A (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Washington University: Working Drawings (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Washington University: Sketches for Advanced Design Project (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Schoolhouse for the Twenty-first Century (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Washington University [Alumni Files] (Box 1, Folder 20-22)
  - Civic Society
    - Chattanooga Community Model City Affairs (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Huntsville Model Homes (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Huntsville Sketches (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - The City (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Model City (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Great Decisions (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Huntsville Council on Human Relations (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Huntsville Arts League and Museum Association (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Civic Engagement/LTE's Clippings (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Huntsville League of Women Voters (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Architecture Talks/Model City (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series II: Professional Papers
  - Associations and Committees
    - Washington D.C., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - AIA National Convention, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - AIA Bulletins (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - AIA Meeting, St. Louis (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - AIA (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - AIA Membership Committee (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - AIA Public Relationship Committee (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - AIA Bus Tours (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - AIA Tours (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - AIA Speakers (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - AIA Meeting-St. Louis (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Alpha Alpha Gamma-AWA (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - History of AWA (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Los Angeles Chapter-AWA (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Alpha Alpha Gamma & AIA St. Louis, Monsanto (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Alpha Alpha Gamma: Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Association of Women in Architecture (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Architecture in St. Louis: Twelve Historic Structures (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
    - Architecture in St. Louis: Twelve Contemporary Buildings (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Women's Architectural League-President (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Women's Architectural League (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Women's Architectural League-Speaker's Bureau (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Conferences
    - International Design Conference in Aspen (1964) (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - International Design Conference in Aspen (1966) (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Aspen 1966-Notes (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - International Design Conference (1968) (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Congress on American Women Leaders, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Writings
    - Richard Neutra (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Union Station Supplement to WAL's "Historic Structures" (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - M.L.'s Chapter for AIA Book on St. Louis Architecture (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Research Notes
    - Notes for "Survival Through Design" (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Notes for "Doctor's Offices and Clinics: Medical and Dental" (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Notes for "The Natural House" (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - An American Architecture (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Reference Files
    - Articles on Architecture (Box 3, Folder 14-21)
    - H. May Steinmesch: Architect 1930s (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - St. Louis Building Code P.W. Martin Room 208 City Hall (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - AEC Architecture in St. Louis (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - St. Louis EADs Bridge., 1904, W.F., Brick, Proetz (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Knoll au Louvre 1972 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - The Stephens Chairs - Knoll International (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Knoll Index of Contemporary Design (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Construction (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    - Face Brick Tables (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Yellow Pine Timbers Booklet (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Patios (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Decorating Planning (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Pencil Sketching-Watson (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Worlds Fair Houses - 1932-1933, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - "House of the Modern Age": Park Avenue at Thirty-ninth Street, New York" (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - The Architectural Forum: Including "Building Money" (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - House & Home, Sept. 1936 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "House Beautiful Building Manual: New Produces, Plans, Designs", Spring 1936 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Planning and Remodeling Bathrooms (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Your Second Home: Masonite Corporation (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Open House: Reviewing Your New Wood (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Panelfold Doors Pamphlet, n.d. (Box 10)
    - General Specifications for Your New Home, n.d. (Box 10)
    - Crane: Modern Kitchen Equipment, n.d. (Box 10)
    - Home Planners Inc, "Good Details", n.d. (Box 8)
- Series III: Office Records
  - Architecture Notes (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Mary Lou Drosten: Design (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Drosten Designs (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Drosten Design Construction Notes (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Construction Photos (project unknown), May 1962 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Series IV: Project Records
  - Bodley, Don and Judy (3790 Cuscawilla Trail, Chattanooga, TN; 1964; bathroom remodel) (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Bodley, Don and Judy (3003 Ozark Road, Chattanooga, TN; 1965-1968; interior design) (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Bomze, Howard (6942 Waterman Avenue, University City, MO; 1975; landscape) (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Bomze, Howard (6942 Waterman Avenue, University City, MO; 1976; screened porch) (Box 7)
  - Brigham Jr., H.F. (4 Narraganset, Ladue, MO; 1976; residence addition) (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Brock Construction Co. (Chattanooga, TN; 1962; exterior aesthetic suggestions) (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Brownlee, Roland (939 Talley Road, Chattanooga, Tn; 1962; garden, terrace and interior design) (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Burgess, Hubert (1634 Greenhills Drive, Hixson, TN; 1964; interior design) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Bus shelter (Stuart Heights Garden Club, Chattanooga, TN; 1964; proposed bus shelter design) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Cherry, James D (7425 Kingsbury, Uniersity City, MO; 1975; garden design) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Children's Clinic (Green & Miller, 304 Ashland Terrace, Chattanooga, TN; 1956; design and oversight of construction) (Box 5, Folder 6-9, Box 15)
  - Community Garden (South Side, 6600 block of Delmar Blvd, University City, MO; 1977; proposed garden for vacant lot) (Box 5, Folder 11, Box 10)
  - Chattanooga Unitarian Church (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Crenshaw Clinic (St. Louis, MO; 1934; dental clinic (first job)) (Box 7)
  - Davis, Robert S. (6911 Waterman Avenue, University City, MO; 1979; kitchen renovation) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Derthick & Henley (Chattanooga architectural firm; 1962; drafting job, proposed bell tower for methodist church) (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Dorris, Andrew and Barbara (6370 Waterman Avenue, University City, MO; 1977; foundation planting) (Box 5, Folder 14-15, Box 10)
  - Drosten, Fred and Mary Lou (46 Rye Lane, St. Louis MO; 1938; architect's residence) (Box 5, Folder 16-21, Box 8,9,13)
  - Drosten, Fred and Mary Lou (2883 Stuart Terrace, Chattanooga, TN; 1955; architect's residence) (Box 5, Folder 22-36, Box 8,11,13)
  - Drosten, Fred and Mary Lou (945 Old Bonhomme Rd, University City, MO; 1979; addition to architect's home) (Box 6, Folder 1, Box 11)
  - Falkowski, Edward and Evelyn (2206 East Governors Drive, Huntsville, AL; 1966; interior/exterior decoration) (Box 6, Folder 2, Box 11)
  - Folts, Bishop, and Thomas Office (Provident Building, Chattanooga, TN) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Gibson, Raymond (Regal and Berkeley Red Bank, TN; 1964; plan revisions) (Box 6, Folder 4, Box 11, 13)
  - Graham, Dr. & Mrs. Frank B. (211 Shallowford Road, Chattanooga, TN; 1958; sketches drive & residence) (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - Gronaua, Drs. Axel and Marianna (7062 Waterman Avenue, University City, MO; 1975; kitchen flooring) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Harford, Dr. and Mrs. Carl G. (6940 Waterman Avenue, University City, MO; 1970; porch and deck) (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Harford, Dr. and Mrs. Carl G. (6940 Waterman Avenue, University City, MO; 1978; kitchen renovation) (Box 6, Folder 10, Box 10)
  - Hayden, Mr. and Mrs. Donald (2918 Nurick Drive, Chattanooga, TN; 1962; garage change and repairs) (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Hayes, Tom & Paula (6926 Dartmouth Avenue, University City, MO; 1978; double decker screen porch) (Box 7)
  - Hayes, Tom & Paula (6926 Dartmouth Avenue, University City, MO; 1974; kitchen and bathroom) (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Kruesi, Paul R. (302 Arrow Drive, Signal Mountain, TN; 1962; consultant and figures) (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Kushner, Peter and Pinky (2633 Harris St., Eugene, OR; 1978; suggested revisions (not executed)) (Box 10)
  - Levine, Charles (Altamont Road, Chattanooga, TN; 1957; residence) (Box 6, Folder 14, Box 12)
  - Livingston, Dr. and Mrs Phillip (111 Provident Building, Chattanooga, TN; 1960; interior design of medical office) (Box 6, Folder 15, Box 14)
  - Livingston, Dr. and Mrs Phillip (1718 Minnekahda Road, Chattanooga, TN; 1956; overseer for Richard Neutra project; interior design of medical office; cd of letters w/ Neutra) (Box 6, Folder 16-19)
  - Loeffel, Dr. Ellen (Rooms 201-211, 425 DeBaliviere, St. Louise, MO; 1945; interior design of medical office) (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Marsh, Mr. and Mrs. Fred (Carroll Lane, Chattanooga, TN; 1959; plan preparation) (Box 6, Folder 21, Box 12)
  - Memorial Baptist Church (Red Bank, TN; 1959; sketches, classrooms, etc) (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Metcalf, Richard P. and Margaret (346 East Drive, Oak Ridge, TN; 1964; remodel w/ balcony & interior design) (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Miller, Dr. Robert T. (Minnekahda Road, Chattanooga, TN; 1957; house design) (Box 6, Folder 26, Box 12)
  - Nelson, Mrs. Anita (Lancaster Avenue, Red Bank, TN; 1963; house placement) (Box 6, Folder 27, Box 11)
  - Oak Ridge Township, Tennessee (Oak Ridge, TN; 1948-50; high school renovation) (Box 6, Folder 24-25)
  - Poss, Mr. and Mrs. H.M. (319 Buena Vista Drive, Chattanooga, TN; 1962; rainwater drainage and patio) (Box 6, Folder 28, Box 13)
  - Rivard, Loren and Caroline (Baltimore, MD; 1977; proposed renovation) (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Robinson, W.W. Mr. and Mrs. (Forest Park Drive, Signal Mountain, TN; 1963; interior design) (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Rudner, Dr. and Mrs. Richard (6939 Waterman Avenue, University City, MO; 1977; landscape plans) (Box 6, Folder 31, Box 7)
  - Rust, Mr. and Mrs. Jack (102 Windmere Chattanooga, TN; 1965; bathroom remodel) (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Shavin, Seymour and Gerte (334 North Crest Road, Chattanooga, TN; 1977; interior design for Wright house) (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Shearer, Dr. Wayne (306 Ashland Terrace, Chattanooga, TN; 1963; optometric clinic) (Box 6, Folder 34-35, Box 15)
  - Shearer, Dr. Wayne (122 Valley Brook Road, Hixson, TN; 1965; consultation on house design) (Box 6, Folder 36, Box 7)
  - Solomon, Jay and Rosalind (2932 Folts Drive, Chattanooga, TN; 1958; remodel for residence) (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Sotlongs Tennis Court (unknown; 1962; Tennis court) (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Thomas, Elmer (1111 and 1113 East Third Street Chattanooga, TN; 1958-63; commercial building consultation) (Box 6, Folder 39, Box 11)
  - Trundle, Dr. Frank (2943 Folts Circle, Chattanooga, TN; 1961; residential design) (Box 6, Folder 40-41, Box 7,12)
  - Weil, Mark L. (1201 Westmoreland Ave., SE Huntsville, AL; 1967; landscape design) (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Weinberg, Morris and Janie Mae (8601 Clarendon Lane, Hixson, TN; 1964; addition to residence) (Box 6, Folder 42)